A Guide to the Papers of Henry James, 1855-1969, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
  - Subseries B: Undated Henry James Correspondence
    - Henry James to [Anne Thackeray] Ritchie, n.y. May 6, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 8:90)
      Spent 2-3 days looking for article on Browning, but cannot locate it. Doesn't think she would have found it useful; it was clumsy and uninspired. Has seen Leslie and Stephen. Fears he is weakened by his illness. Glad she is in good form. Wishes she didn't live so far away. He lunches out only on Sunday, when he can start out early, so dear is morning to him. #6251-y
    - Henry James to Mr. Robinson, n.y. October 26, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 8:91)
      Appreciates letter. Is in situation of helplessness in which smallest assistance is thankfully received. Notes names of roses he gives him. Is not going in for "roses," etc. His aspirations are humble. His garden needs "making." His dream is a small and old-fashioned formal garden. If he had a caring friend, he would put the case into his hands and leave him free. Obliged for his sympathy and other contributions. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. Rogerson, n.y. October 24, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 8:92)
      Thanks, with delight. Will come Tuesday and embrace her mother, after that she may be the affectionate one. #6251-m
    - Henry James to Mrs. Simpson, n.y. November 25, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 8:93)
      Has made plans to leave town for a few weeks so is deprived of the pleasure of dining with her. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. [George Washburn] Smalley, n.d. "Saturday,", ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 8:94)
      Sends rest of letters back, with sense of their beauty and interest being confirmed. They are a mine of charming and touching characteristic things, doing honor to everyone concerned. They will contribute immensely to the illumination of his name. He is homesick before going and feels his return would be early. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. Sturgis, n.d. "Friday,", ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 8:95)
      The 4:55 from Victoria tomorrow will be the most feasible train. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Juliet] Trower n.y. May 8, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:1)
      Her proposals are delightful, but they find him helpless and unable to leave town. P.S. Doesn't deserve that she still kindly reads him. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Juliet] Trower, n.d. "Monday,", ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:2)
      Impossible to avail self of her kind invitation. Will pounce on her in town if she ever comes back. Regrets his hatred of his impediment. #6251-m
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Juliet] Trower, n.d. "Monday,", ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:3)
      Thought it discreet not to follow up her offer to bind him a little book, but he ventures to send her one: a small volume of Anatole France, which is a masterpiece and on which her graceful art will not be wasted. He shall value the result of her handiwork, but take it very easily, and operate all at her leisure. Has charming memory of their Sunday together. #6251-v
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Juliet] Trower, n.d. "Thursday,", ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:4)
      Encloses prescription if she will kindly let him have it again. Its name appears to be peperazine, and its nature magical. Revealed to his Dr. four months ago by Sir Andrew Clark. Available at best chemists; he couldn't get it in Paris. It is expensive but it works fast. May it renew her youth! #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. [John Symonds] Vidler, n.d. "Wednesday,", ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:5)
      Sorry but error is wholly his. Wrote memo for wrong date. Let him come some other near day. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. [John Symonds] Vidler, n.d. "Wednesday,", ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:6)
      Will give him much pleasure to come to her garden fête. Waited because he thought he would have to go to town, but glad the menace lifted. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. [John Symonds] Vidler, n.d. "Wednesday,", ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:7)
      Will give him great pleasure to dine tomorrow. Excuse him for not dressing as he didn't bring to Rye the wherewithal. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. [John Symonds] Vidler, n.d. "Wednesday,", ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:8)
      Forgive him for keeping her little book so long, but it got thrust out of sight by mistake. He never puts anything but his small signature to which she is welcome. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. [John Symonds] Vidler, n.d. "Friday,", ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:9)
      Will give his friend Jonathan Sturgis and him great pleasure to dine with her tomorrow at 7:30 p.m. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Humphrey] Ward, n.d. "Tuesday,", ALS, 4 pp. (Box-folder 9:10)
      Grieves to say he will not be well enough to dine with her Friday. He has had a sorry and stricken time, with a baffled recuperation, and social intercourse this week is out of the question. In 2-3 days he will go to Torquay for a fortnight. Otherwise, he shall simply bolt home. #6251-a
    - H[enry] James to Mrs. Waring, n.y. December 3, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:11)
      Sorry he is nailed for Friday. Sends thanks and regrets. Shall see her before he goes. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Barrett Wendell, n.y. December 3, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:12)
      His notes on Chicago Fair kindled his imagination and revived his memory of his too short and too distant visit. Pages in Harvard Magazine are delightful. Doesn't regret not having been one of the gazers and gapers; he is too fond of reflected light. Always more interested in effects produced than in producing force. #6251-a
  - Subseries C: Other Correspondents
    - Donald [Brien?] to Edna [Kenton] [1951?] January 29, ALS, 3 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 9:13)
      Sorry to hear of her brothers' troubles. Louise will be happy to have The Galaxy papers and add a Trollope title to her shelf of that unabashed teller of good yarns. Japanese news. Sure LeRoy Phillips glad to have the eight uncollected; he is a very grateful person. [Thomas Sergeant] Perry biography has had no reviews. He does not want to review it, but the James letters was like boring through solid granite. Not a Perry fan, and thinks all of his portraits confirm a stolidity. However, do send the letters as he could be so wrong. Gives a detailed account of the James letters and despairs over a twenty year lapse from 1886 to 1906. #6251-m
    - Cyril Clemens to [Leon] Edel, 1943 April 18, APCS, 1 item (Box-folder 9:14)
      Regarding symposium for Henry James's Century. Would like to know if he would participate. #6251-bi
    - Leon [Edel] to Edna [Kenton], 1950 November 15, APCS, 1 item. (Box-folder 9:15)
      Scott Tunstall is the right one for Hugh Walpole. He was fascinated by Scott all his life. Thought himself the modern Sir Walter. He did finally get the Sir! #6251-m
    - Leon [Edel] to Edna [Kenton], [1950 May 14], TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 9:16)
      Wonderful review she did in the Kenyon. Hers is the only review that has seen the point of the "story of the story." That she did doesn't surprise him. Small minds will say that they are friends, but they are not concerned with small minds. Still, there can be no question of her "disinterestedness." He prizes her review the most, and since they are friends, he feels her reviews are even more objective and exacting. Hopes to tell her face to face how deeply he appreciates her work. Passes along news of Donald's illness. #6251-m
    - Leon [Edel] to Edna [Kenton], 1953 May 11, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 9:17)
      Belated thanks her kind letter on receiving the book. Reviews have been good. Good for the Henry James reputation in tearing away a lot of cobwebs. Princeton a wonderful experience. Will get in touch with her at the end of the month. Worried about Donald. #6251-m
    - Leon [Edel] to Edna [Kenton], 1953 December 17, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:18)
      Students engulfed him after the fall reunion. Promises that he will get into touch with her in the new year and make a date for another long talk. Off to Chicago to attend a gathering of pundits. #6251-m
    - EG [Edmund Gosse] and NG to Henry James, n.d., ANS, 1 item. (Box-folder 9:19)
      "From his affectionate friends." #6251-an
    - "E.S.H." [of J. B. Lippincott Company] to "P.L." 1916 April 8, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:20)
      Regarding In the Cage. Thinks it one of the most wonderful pieces James did. Has read it over and over. The way he worked it out is marvelous. The scene of Captain Everard and the girl on the beach one of the most delicate pieces in literature. #6251-u
    - H. Montgomery Hyde to [Clifton] Waller [Barrett], 1969 April 23, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:21)
      The long delayed publication of Henry James At Home takes place tomorrow, appearing in the United States in the fall. Decided not to use his portrait of James as a frontispiece. Good reproduction proves difficult. Using original Sargent drawing. Has not forgotten to present the manuscript to the University of Virginia. Will hold on to it until publication in America. Wonders if the Grolier Club would like him to talk about the book. His cousin recently died of a sudden heart attack, and will dedicate his book to him and his wife, Holly. #6251-aw
    - H. Montgomery Hyde to [Clifton] Waller [Barrett], 1969 September 1, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:22)
      Thanks for his letter. Happy that he can participate in the Grolier Club function. No one can introduce him better than Barrett could. Very grateful. Wonders if he should come to Charlottesville for a night so he could hand over his manuscript. Otherwise will give it to him in New York. Looks forward to hearing from him. #6251-ab
    - Alice James to [Edna] Kenton, 1950 May 8, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:23)
      Giving information about Mrs. Francis Ford who has been traced by Mr. Percy Lubbock. #6251-m
    - Alice James to [Edna] Kenton, 1950 August 1, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 9:24)
      Would like letters of Mr. Percy Lubbock about Mrs. Francis Ford returned. #6251-m
    - Alice James to [Edna] Kenton, 1952 April 7, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:25)
      Sends an Easter box. Looks forward to meeting. #6251-m
    - Alice James to Edna [Kenton], 1953 May 17, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:26)
      Was pleasant satisfaction to meet. Have been absorbed by Leon [Edel]'s life of Uncle Henry. Admires it and is fascinated by it and cannot wait until next volume. #6251-m
    - Henry James, III to Roger Scaife, 1930 August 7, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:27)
      Encloses a clean copy of the Preface [not present], which completes the manuscript. Burden now shifted to his shoulders. Wishes him luck. #6251-m
    - H[enry] James [Sr.] to "My dear friend," 1855 April 8, ALS, 7 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 9:28)
      Gave no one the right to say that he either in theory or practice regards their present social bonds as vicious simply because they are imperfect. Time will come when a perfect society or fellowship will prevail among men. But it would be absurd to say that coercion was out of place in the present even with his beliefs about the future. This would be bad logic and worse legislation. Gives analogies to their situation. The future is to be secured only on the condition of a rigid fidelity to the law of its present. Wants him to send a formal note for the Tribune requesting him to define his position. He will rejoice in the opportunity. P.S. Wife sends her love to him. #6251-a
    - H[enry] James [Sr.] to "My dear Ripley," [ca. 1863] September 15, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. mounted. (Box-folder 9:29)
      Wrote a readable article about Barrett's book on the Lacedaemonians, ventilating his ancient animosity in a pleasant way. Could he publish it? Can use his name if he likes. P.S. Please tell Greeley or Mr. Gay that they will find in the 7th book of the Peloponnesian War of Thucydides, 27th chapter, an instance of the liberation of slaves of an enemy, operated by the Spartans against the Athenians. #6251-ap
    - H[enry] J[ames] [Sr.] to "My dear H. E. H." [Hattie E. Hathaway], [1874] February 19, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:30)
      Attached to group of documents entitled Curiosities of Literature, which provides a brief description of the items included in attachment: "To me, these letters seem but the senile sentimentality which Age often displays toward feminine youth." Attached are two clippings, Spiritualism New and Old and the Death Penalty- A Substitute for the Gallows, by Henry James and an anonymous letter, n.d. Henry James to Hattie E. Hathaway: "You give me your address but do not know if you call me friend or whether you are an old correspondent. What is the trouble you are suffering from? You naturally excite my desire to know what diseases I can relieve." Sends her some articles [included]. Tell him when she receives articles, the circumstances under which she expects it to be applicable, and whether she still continues of that mind. * Anonymous letter [from Hattie E. Hathaway?]: Thanks for the articles, which have satisfied certain longings, but exacted others which she fears will be long in the satisfying. Moreover, it is quite certain she is not his "old correspondent," for she never wrote him until last week, and she is just as ignorant of the other member of the Hathaway family that he mentioned. #6251-bc
    - H[enry] J[ames] [Sr.] to "My dear H. E. H." [Hattie E. Hathaway], [ ca. 1874], ALSs, 40 pp. (Box-folder 9:31)
      Four attached letters, dated February 25, February 28, March 4, March 17 to Hattie E. Hathaway. * February 25, ca. 1874: Yesterday was pregnant with snow and tempest, but today is bright and peaceful enough to counterfeit heaven to one's sensuous regard. Contrasts his "inward meteorological change" with the changes in the weather. Continues with a metaphor of a ship in a river-bed when the tide is out. And he, like the ship when the tide comes in, upon a wave of womanly influence into his heart and mind, leaves him no voice but worship. Never was a letter more surcharged with the effluence of womanhood. Accepts an invitation to meet a company of ladies and gentlemen this evening. Gives his thanks to invitation. Yesterday she was an ordinary person; today she is holy and stainless to his imagination. Blesses her for being what God has made of her, your faithful friend forever henceforth. * February 28, ca. 1874: Sends reply to her letter. Feels devout joy and responds to the new force of womanhood. It is not the literal woman, but the invisible woman, the aromatic, unconscious person who appeals to the spiritual senses primarily. She sends exquisite grace, and was kissing in imagination the sweet white feet of her innocence, and looking up with devotion to the blue over-arching heaven of her womanly eyes and face. Gives her advice about the people who feel prejudice about her. Discusses at length his philosophy of Society. It is their divine destiny to know this philosophy. * March 4, ca. 1874: Profusely thanks her for her most recent letter. Discusses the "New Marriage Sentiment" in her bosom, which is so fast coming to renew the earth, and take up the despised and degraded and crucified form of sexual love into its renovating arms. He feels her profound marriage-life throbbing in her letters, and yearns to give it consciousness. Tells her of the ritual, which is nothing apart from itself, which he is sure she would be eager to acknowledge. He could prompt its development in her, which he does with all his heart, and she will be born into the truth. Of course being born again or renewed is somewhat painful to fleshly prejudice, but if he holds her in his arms every moment and ministers to her with infinite love, won't it be at least tolerable to her? Write back quickly! * March 17, ca. 1874: Replying to her letter. Sorry he was obscure, but took for granted a gentle familiarity on her part with his ideas about marriage. Will tell fully what he means about the "New Marriage Sentiment" in regards to his marriage. His wife is the greatest blessing of his life, and he is indebted to her. But he and his wife have been tempted against the contractual bond of marriage, and it is a great pity that a greater freedom of divorce not be allowed. Discusses his views on divorce. As for Marriage, in the carnal type of marriage the man represents the universal element in existence, the material element, the gross realistic element; the woman represents the individual element, the spiritual element, and the subtle personal element. Discusses the nature of "free-lovers." Then discusses "thoughtful persons" role in marriage, that they are above the societal restrictions upon marriage, and can combine in a unity that is a friendship as much above love or conjugality as heaven is above earth. Two people can make together the perfect image of the grand society which is coming, which is the universal marriage of all men with all women, and this is the holy verse of spirit. This is his profound conviction. Your postscript says "don't disappoint me," and that urgency is so extremely sweet that he can barely write. #6251-bc
    - [Henry James, Sr.] to [Hattie E. Hathaway], [ca. 1874-1877], ALs, 28 pp. (Box-folder 9:32)
      Four attached letters, dated October 18, November 1, May 9, March 28, to Hattie E. Hathaway. * October 18 [1874?]: Your letter is so fragrant with inspiration that he could not help answering it on the spot, since it is so full of the "new wine" of the kingdom. Curious how one manages to realize these sacred experiences amidst the din of trivialities. Here she is, a person unknown to him by sense, and probably always to be so, though that is not a grateful suggestion to his imagination. It is an ineffable horror to him if the worship he addressed to Him profaned the lower uses, or appropriated by an undevout heart. But she shouldn't worry. Her letters have a certain womanly charm: a charm of perfect grace and freedom. She has associated him with the intimate wants of her life. When she said in her last letter that "though you have yearned for the experimental knowledge of the love flight" that for a long time had scarcely a conscious longing which his blissful secret did not take to its heart. Keep the enclosed letter in your private keeping and keep all his letters shut out from all knowledge but her own, for they are full of a love inspired by Himself and owing nothing in common with the base of the world. * November 1: Fell to influenza that prevented him from writing, but will two points from her last letter. 1. Don't try to think of God incessantly. The divine humanity has always been revealed to man in what is called the church. The church is a purely symbolic institution. Discusses the churches early use of symbols through animals. But the symbols lost their significance, and the church became valued for its own sake. A new revelation of God's perfection consequently took place in Jesus Christ, whose death and resurrection was in essence spiritual. But there is a new change in the church, destitute of all ritual features. Human society is Gods new truth, the society fellowship or equality of all men with each, and of each with all. Thus, don't think of God, for He is all about her, in her bosom above all. 2. She mentions that he would be disappointed if they met. But when the meet he has nothing to do with her in the outward world, but only recognizes her inwardly. But since she is the woman and he is the man he would render her infinite worship. Very anxious to hear from her. * November 9: Still sick, but answers her sweet invitation. Will meet her tomorrow at 3 P.M. and be sure to receive him as he will be very disappointed. Will need to be off by 1. * November 28: What a pleasant sight is her clear, shapely, feminine handwriting. Hoped she would come back once the clouds and darkness bred of illness had lifted. Rejoices in her exquisite and intimate friendship. Wonders if she reads the papers, since he is involved with a controversy with the Editors of the Index, which would be of interest to them. Will send her all his letters but meanwhile tell him whether or not he should do so. Her letters are full of so much womanly grace and sweetness, and so subtle an aroma of womanly charm that he covets them. How sweet it would be to kiss her womanly feet, or find an altar of Divine worship in those gentle feminine hands which have ministered to him so many priestly benedictions. #6251-bc
    - [Henry James, Sr.] to [Hattie E. Hathaway], 1876 January 1, AL, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 9:33)
      Attached to ALS, December 24 [1875?], Henry James, Sr. to Hattie E. Hathaway, 4 pp. on 1 l. * December 24: Tired of waiting for her last response to his last letter of months and months ago. Are you tired of the correspondence? What is the reason you don't write? Reluctant to believe that she is definitively retired from their correspondence. It may be that you are dead and gone to dwell among less noisy people than the Brooklynites, but have recently discovered quite unexpectedly your address, and am going to ascertain if you are not, as I hope, in the land of the living still. * January 1, 1876: Happy New Year. She expresses a great ennui, but the expression is too vague to allow him the expectation of meeting it. But she is suffering from spiritual celibacy, or a sense of almost utter disjunction between their private selfhood and that of the race. The public self and the private self are perfectly one in God, but are declared enemies. His communion with his wife and child being days and hours of uninterrupted peace and harmony. Any chance acquaintance he makes with strangers in horse cars or elsewhere is filled with a Divine aroma that fills him with adoration. Anything that helps his celebrate the Divine unity is his constant want and aspiration. She too is of a true human quality, and would gladly be lifted out of her petty, personal dimension. That is what makes him love her, his sweet H.E.H., and count upon her lasting love, upon a tie of friendship which ennobles all their intercourse. #6251-bc
    - [Henry James, Sr.] to [Hattie E. Hathaway], 1876 April [6], AL, 12 pp. on 3 l. (Box-folder 9:34)